Víctor Ponce López



Contact

vponcelop<at>gmail.com victorponce.info Bristol, United Kingdom

Languages

Catalan ****(native), Spanish ★★★★ (native), English **** (advanced reading/writing,

fluent oral). Français ****

(intermediate reading/writing, basics oral).

Programming Languages, Libs, Tools, **Web and Environments**

Python, MATLAB, C++/C#/C, R, PyCharm, Netbeans, Eclipse, VS/VC++, SVN/GIT, Redmine, LATEX, XML, PostgreSQL, SQL, MySQL, Hive, Spark, Hadoop, CodaLab, Kaggle, Bash, PHP/HTML/CSS/JavaScript;

Deep Learning & Computer

Vision libraries and toolboxes: Tensorflow, PyTorch, Keras, GAN. CNN. LSTM. dlib. CUDA+CuDNN, Kinect™SDK, open{CV/NI/GL}, CNTK+; evolutionary computation and statistical pattern recognition: numpy, matplotlib, sklearn, optimtool, gatool, pmtk3, deap, pandas, statsmodel.

OS Preferences

GNU/Linux **** Windows ★★★★ MacOS **** Android ★★★★ iOS ****

short bio

I am a Research Fellow at the University College London and a Honorary Research Fellow of the Dept. of Computer Science at the University of Bristol and member of the European Laboratory for Learning and Intelligent Systems (ELLIS). I was a Research Scientist in Eurecat at the Big Data Analytics Unit. I hold a PhD at the the Dept. of Mathematics and Computer Science, University of Barcelona (UB). I received my B.Sc. degree in Computer Science and Engineering at the Faculty of Mathematics of UB, and my M.Sc. degree in Artificial Intelligence at the Polytechnic University of Catalonia. I was affiliated to the Computer Vision Center and the Open University of Catalonia, in the groups HuPBA and SUNAI; and the group Qarma at the Laboratoire d'Informatique Fondamentalle, Aix-Marseille Université.

experience

2017-Present **University College London & University of Bristol**

Bristol & London, United Kingdom Member of the European Laboratory for Learning and Intelligent Systems (ELLIS).

Barcelona, Spain

Postdoctoral Research Associate & Fellow

• Machine Learning and Natural Language Processing for Environment & Energy.

• Time-Series Prediction of Seasonal Ground Surface Deformation.

• Computer Vision for Human Activity Recognition in Home Healthcare.

• Domain Adaptation, Self-Supervised Learning, GANs, Person Re-IDentification.

2010-2017 Eurecat Technology Center of Catalonia, University of Barcelona, Open University of Catalonia, Computer Vision Center, and Dept. of Justice, Government of Catalonia

> Research Scientist, PostDoc, Collaboration in Research projects, international PhD stay, 40+ scientific publications and peer-reviews, teaching and material preparation, organization/attendance on international conferences, events, and seminars.

• 4 impact factor journals, 17 conference proceedings, and 1 book chapter.

• ChaLearn Looking At People collaboration with Microsoft, NVIDIA, Google, Amazon, Disney, Facebook, Orange, MWC-GSMA.

· Research projects on human behavior analysis within real-world domains.

Past-2010 Barcelona's Council: Dept. of Education, Culture and Welfare

Software Engineer, IT Services.

education

2012-2016 Ph.D. in Mathematics and Computer Science

Faculty of Mathematics, University of Barcelona

Dissertation: "Evolutionary Bags of Space-Time Features for Human Analysis." Cum

Laude (spanish) and International Mention.

2010-2012 M.Sc in Artificial Intelligence

Polytechnic University of Catalonia, University of Barcelona, and Rovira i Virgili University.

Dissertation: "Multi-Modal Human Gesture Recognition combining Dynamic Program-

ming and Probabilistic Methods." With Honors.

2006-2010 **B.Sc in Computer Science: Systems engineering**

Faculty of Mathematics, University of Barcelona.

Dissertation: "Analysis of Oral and Gestural Expression using an Artificial Vision Sys-

tem." With Honors.

extracurricular

2006-Present **Driving license**

1998-2004 Musical language and Piano licenses

interests

I'm a research & technology passionate. My main interests are computer vision, machine learning, and evolutionary computation for real-world applications. I like to be up to date with latest research and cutting-edge technology to foresee next future trends and needs.

PARTICIPATION IN RESEARCH PROJECTS AND TECHNOLOGICAL TRANSFER:

Project Title: Digital Environment for the Analysis and Detection of Ground Surface Deformation.

Funding Entity: UK Research and Innovation.

Participant Entities: University of Bristol, SatSense, Terrafirma, TRE-Altamira.

Duration: 2019/05/20 to 2019/12/23. **Project Responsible**: Juliet Biggs. **Number of Researchers involved**: >10

Project Title: SPHERE, a Sensor Platform for HEalthcare in a Residential Environment.

Funding Entity: EPSRC (Engineering and Physical Sciences Research Council), University of

Bristol.

Participant Entities: IBM, Toshiba, Bristol City Council, Universities of Southampton, Cambridge

and Reading, KWMC.

Duration: 2017/01/31 to 2022/01/31.

Project Responsible: Ian Craddock, Majid Mirmehdi, Dima Damen.

Number of Researchers involved: >50

Project Title: eTur 2020.

Funding Entity: Centro para el Desarrollo Tecnológico Industrial (CDTI), MINECO, Spanish

Government.

Participant Entities: Tecnocom, Groupalia, Eurecat, Eurona, Solusoft, Compartia, Zemsania.

Duration: from 2017/05/05 to 2017/09/31.

Project Responsible: Jesus Carlos Villagra Laso, Jose Mena Roldan, Marc Torrent, Víctor Ponce

López.

Number of Researchers involved: >10

Project Title: Tourism Management.

Funding Entity: Barcelona Council, GSM, and Mobile World Capital.

Participant Entities: Barcelona Council, Orange, GSM, MWC, Eurecat, DFRC, D-Lab.

Duration: from 2017/02/15 to 2018/04/31.

Project Responsible: Marc Torrent Moreno, Bárbara Vallespín Peré.

Number of Researchers involved: >10

Project Title: New Technologies for Virtual and Augmented Reality (VR360).

Funding Entity: Eurecat, Government of Catalonia.

Participant Entities: Eurecat Tecnology Center of Catalonia, Computer Vision Center.

Duration: from 2017/04/01 to 2018/12/31. Project Responsible: Rafael Redondo. Number of Researchers involved: >10

Project Title: Social Car.

Funding Entity: European Union Horizon 2020 No 636427.

Participant Entities: CERTH, MOVENDA, TAXISTOP, SUPSI, UWH, ZIGHT, ABACUS,

STRATEGIC STUFF, UNIABDN, IBI Group, FIT, VECTOS, BERMAG, TTS Italia, Eurecat.

Duration: from 2015/09/01 to 2017/11/31.

Proiect Responsible: Dionisis Kehagias, Andrea Emilio Rizzoli

Number of Researchers involved: >10

Project Title: ChaLearn Looking at People: Apparent Personality Analysis on First Impressions.

Funding Entity: ChaLearn.

Participant Entities: Microsoft Research, NVIDIA, Amazon, Google, Disney Research, Aix-Marseille Université, *Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona* (UAB), *Universitat de Barcelona* (UB),

Universitat Oberta de Catalunya (UOC). **Duration**: from 2014/09/22 to 2016/11/31.

Project Responsible: Isabelle Guyon, Sergio Escalera.

Number of Researchers involved: >20

Project Title: ChaLearn Looking at People: Gesture Challenge.

Funding Entity: European Conference on Computer Vision (ECCV) 2014, ChaLearn.

Participant Entities: Microsoft Research, Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona (UAB), Universitat

de Barcelona (UB), Universitat Oberta de Catalunya (UOC).

Duration: from 2013/12/09 to 2014/10/12

Project Responsible: Isabelle Guyon, Sergio Escalera.

Number of Researchers involved: >20

Project Title: Spatio-Temporal Sub-Gesture Definition for Automatic Human Behaviour Analysis.

Funding Entity: FI-DGR 2013. AGAUR, Generalitat of Catalonia.

Participant Entities: Open University of Barcelona (UOC).

Duration: from 2013/02/01 until 2016/01/31 **Project Responsible**: Xavier Baró Solé. **Number of Researchers involved**: 5

Project Title: ReMedi: Multi-modal Home Assistive Technology for Dementia and Alzheimer's

Diseases.

Funding Entity: Obra Social La Caixa.

Participant Entities: Bosch and Gimpera Foundation (FBG), University of Barcelona.

Duration: from 2012/04/01 until 2013/01/31 **Project Responsible**: Oriol Pujol Vila. **Number of Researchers involved**: 7

Project Title: Human Behaviour Analysis in Victim-Offender Mediations. **Funding Entity**: Department of Justice of the *Generalitat* of Catalonia.

Duration: from 2012/02/01 until 2013/03/31

Project Responsibles: Víctor Ponce López, Sergio Escalera Guerrero, Xavier Baró Solé.

Number of Researchers involved: 5

Project Title: Analysis of Oral and Gestural Expression using an Artificial Vision System.

Funding Entity: University of Barcelona. **Duration**: from: 2010/06/01 until 2010/11/01

Project Responsible: Sergio Escalera, Xavier Baró, Miguel A. Bautista, Víctor Ponce, Verónica

Violant.

Number of Researchers involved: 8

SCHOLARSHIPS AND GRANTS:

- 2019: **UKRI Grant** from UK Research and Innovation for Research Projects in Digital Environment.
- 2017: **EPSRC and IRC Grants**, UK Engineering and Physical Sciences and International Research Councils, Grant *EP/K031910/1*.
- 2016: Research support provided by Microsoft Research, Microsoft CodaLab, the Laboratoire de Recherche en Informatique of Paris Sud University, INRIA-Saclay and the Paris-Saclay Center for Data Science (CDS).
- 2015: **European Comission Horizon 2020 (H2020)** granted project SEE.4C under call *H2020-ICT 2015*.
 - **Grant** to support research projects of consolidated groups by the Ministry of Economy and Competitiveness, **Spanish Government**. *TIN2015-66951-C2-2-R*.
- 2014: Labex ARCHIMEDE Grant for a Research Project. Marseille INstitute of MAthematics and Computer Science (MIN-MACS). Laboratoire d'Informatique Fondamentalle, Aix-Marseille Université, UMR CNRS 7279.
- 2013: **FI-DGR 2013 Grant** for **Formation in Research** from the 'Agència de Gestió d'Ajuts Universitaris i de Recerca' (AGAUR), **Generalitat, Catalan Government.** 2013FI-B01037.
 - **Grant** to support Spanish research projects of consolidated groups by the Ministry of Economy and Competitiveness, **Spanish Government**. *TIN2013-43478-P*.
- 2012: **PMID Grant** for **Teaching Innovation Projects** from **University of Barcelona**. Code: 2012PID-UB/152.
 - **Grant** to support research projects of consolidated groups by the Ministry of Economy and Competitiveness, **Spanish Government**. *TIN2012-38187-C03-02*.
 - **CEJFE Grant** for a research project with the **Department of Justice** (**Generalitat of Catalonia**). Center of Legal Studies and Specialized Formation. Resolution id: JUS/237/2011.
 - **Grant** from *Obra Social La Caixa* for a **Research Project** at the Department of Applied Mathematics and Analysis of the **University of Barcelona**. Grant id: *5800201204001*.
- 2011: **Scholarship** for **Web administration** of the **Faculty of Mathematics** of the University of Barcelona. Code: 1-11PUI.
 - **Grant** to support research projects from IMSERSO, Ministry of Sanity, **Spanish Government**. *MEDIMINDER*.
 - **Grant** to support research and technological projects from RecerCaixa. *REMEDI*.
- 2010: **Collaboration Scholarship** for **Teaching Innovation Projects** with the Department of Applied Mathematics and Analysis of the **University of Barcelona**. *Code: 2-10ESC*.
- 2009: **PMID Grant** for **Teaching Innovation Projects** from **University of Barcelona**. Code: 2009PID-UB/04.

OTHER PUBLIC AND PRIVATE PROJECTS INVOLVED:

- 2020-
- present: **Post-Doctoral Research Fellow** at the University College London.
- 2018-
- present: Honorary Research Fellow at the University of Bristol.
- 2017-
- 2019: Post-Doctoral Research Associate at the University of Bristol.
- 2016: **Research Scientist** at Eurecat, Technology Centre of Catalonia.
- 2016: Post-Doc Researcher at the Computer Vision Center, Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona.
- 2010: **Software Engineer and IT Services** at the Education Management, Culture and Welfare of the **Barcelona Council**.

• PEER REVIEWING (Verified by https://publons.com/a/1202458) (Year) (#Reviews)

- o IEEE Transactions on Evolutionary Computation 2019(1).
- British Machine Vision Conference (BMVC), 2019(4)
- IEEE Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition, Explanatory Computer Vision Workshop ECVW @ CVPR, 2017(1).
- IEEE Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition, Deep Vision Workshop DV2017 @ CVPR, 2017(1).
- o IEEE Transactions on Affective Computing, 2017(2).
- IET Computer Vision 2016(1) 2017(3).
- o On Editorial Board Membership for IEEE Transactions on Affective Computing, 2016.
- o IEEE International Conference on Automatic Face and Gesture Recognition (FG), 2016(2)-2017(2)-2018(4)-2019(1).
- IEEE European Conference on Computer Vision (ECCV) Workshops, 2014(2) 2016 (2).
- IEEE Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR) Conference Workshops, 2016 (3).
- IEEE International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCV) Workshops, 2015 (committee member).
- IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence (TPAMI), 2015 (5).
- IEEE Transactions on Multimedia, 2014(1).

o Journal of Machine Learning Research (JMLR), 2013(1) - 2014(2).

• ORGANIZATION AND SCIENTIFIC PROGRAM COMMITTEE (PC) MEMBER:

- Member of the European Laboratory for Learning and Intelligent Systems (ELLIS).
- Mentor at the ImaginChallenge 2016. Obra Social La Caixa.
- o ECCV 2016 Workshop ChaLearn Looking at People: First Impressions.
- CVCR&D 2016 Workshop: Computer Vision Center, Research and Development advances.
- o ECCV 2014 Workshop ChaLearn Looking at People: Gesture Recognition.
- CCIA 2014 Member of the organization.
- ICCV 2011 Member of the organization.

PARTICIPATION IN CONFERENCES AND SEMINARS:

- o Digital Environment Stakeholder Workshop Meeting, 2019, Engineering House, Bristol
- o International Conference on Image Analysis and Processing (ICIAP), 2019.
- European Conference on Computer Vision (ECCV) Person-In-Context Workshop, 2018.
- British Machine Vision Association (BMVA) Symposium, Technical meeting in Computer Vision for Smart Environments and Assisted Living.
- Bristol Vision Institute Research Colloquium, 2018. Participant and assistant.
- >10 seminars from the Bristol Vision Institute, Visual Information Lab, and SPHERE, at the University of Bristol. Participation and assistant.
- Mobile World Congress, Exhibitor Staff at the Big Data Innovation City (Hall 4), 2017, Barcelona.
- European Workshop on Reinforcement Learning (EWRL), 2016, Barcelona. Assistant.
- o Intel Code Modernization Workshop 2016, Barcelona. Assistant.
- Big Data Congress and Eurecat Mobile Forum 2016, Barcelona. Participant and assistant.
- Assistance in more than 20 seminars covering different areas in the Artificial Intelligence and Computer Vision at the Computer Vision Center of the UAB in the range of years between 2010-2016.
- Deep learning Seminar meetups at Polytechnic University of Catalonia (UPC) and Pompeu Fabra University (UPF), 2016.

- o British Machine Vision Conference (BMVC) 2015. Conference assistant and participant.
- Seminars and workshops held by QARMA group at Centre de Mathématiques et Informatique (CMI). Laboratoire d'Informatique Fondamentale, Aix-Université de Marseille, 2014.
- o European Conference on Computer Vision (ECCV) 2014. Conference assistant and participant. Workshop ChaLearn Looking At People challenge organizer.
- Congrés Internacional de l'Associació Catalana d'Intel·ligència Artificial (CCIA) 2014.
 Facultad de Matemáticas, Universitat de Barcelona. Member of the Committee.
- o *International Conference on Multimodal Interaction (ICMI)* 2013. Coogee Bay Hotel, Sydney, Australia. Conference assistant and participant.
- o First UOC International Research Symposium RDI 2013. Conference assistant and participant.
- ENS/INRIA Computer Vision and Machine Learning Summer School 2013. Assistant and participant.
- o Mobile World Congress (MWC) 2013. Exhibitor Attendee.
- o *International Conference on Pattern Recognition (ICPR)* 2012. Tsukuba Science City, Japan. Conference assistant and participant.
- II Day of Restorative Justice 2012: Experiències restauratives en les comunitats autònomes. Centre d'Estudis Jurídics i Formació Especialitzada (CEJFE), Generalitat of Catalonia.
- o June Seminar 2012: *Humans like watching humans: recent advances in human-centered vídeo analysis*. Assistant at the Computer Vision Center.
- o *Mobile World Congress (MWC)* 2012. Congress assistant.
- International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCV) 2011. Member of the Organization Committee and conference assistant.
- Mediation Talk 2012: Gestural communication in mediation sessions. Center of Legal Studies and Specialized Information, Department of Justice of the Generalitat of Catalonia.
- Workshop CVCR&D 2011. Assistant and participant at the Computer Vision Center. Autonomous University of Barcelona (UAB).
- o International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI) 2011. Conference assistant participant at the Doctoral Consortium.
- July Seminar 2011: Uncertainty in Artificial Intelligence. Assistant at the Computer Vision Center.
- Mobile World Congress (MWC) 2011. Congress assistant.
- December Seminar 2010: Facial Behaviour Understanding. Assistant at the Computer Vision Center.
- Workshop CVCR&D 2010. Assistant and Participant at the Computer Vision Center.

July Seminar 2010: Recognizing Human Actions using Spatio-temporal Interest Points.
 Assistant at the Computer Vision Center.

• TEACHING:

- Co-supervision of B.Sc and M.Sc Students. Thesis at University of Bristol, 2017-2018.
- o Support and preparation of teaching material for the Computer Vision course in the Computer Science degree at the Faculty of Mathematics. University of Barcelona, 2014.
- o Co-supervision of Student's B.Sc. Thesis at University of Barcelona, 2013.
- Grant for Teaching Innovation Projects with code 2012PID-UB/152 from the University of Barcelona.
- Artificial Intelligence Xerrades Taller (Working Talks) at the Faculty of Mathematics (University of Barcelona). Practical Works, Title: "Artificial Intelligence: How do the machines see?" January 2011. Organizer: Dr. Sergio Escalera.
- o ITACA UAB. Days for presenting the Complex Problems and activities in the 'Campus Ítaca' at the Autonomous University of Barcelona. 2010-2015.

HONORS, AWARDS AND OTHER MERITS:

- Author of 4 impact factor journals, 17 conference proceedings and 1 book chapter.
- >40 verified peer-reviews in impact factor journals and international conference proceedings.
- o Runner up for the CERCA Pioneer awards 2016.
- Runner up at the Big Data Talent Awards, Barcelona Big Data Congress 2016.
- International Mention and Cum Laude distinction for the Ph.D. Thesis.
- Obtention of Honors both for B.Sc. and M.Sc. Theses.
- O Award for the best Spanish Bachelor Project by the "Jornadas de Enseñanza Universitaria de la Informática (JENUI) 2010" and posterior publication at the ReVisión Journal of the "Asociación de Enseñantes Universitarios de la Informática (AENUI)", with the work for automatically determine the success of a communication.